[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine
online at computer.org software
[Music]
become an autonomous digital enterprise
and your business can achieve a game
status
intelligent predictive systems
effortless automation
and technology and people working in
harmony
this is the autonomous digital
enterprise
visit bmc.com game for more information
this is kanchan shrinky for software
engineering radio welcome to our show on
ux design for enterprise apps
our guest today is erin baumik aaron has
a masters in human computer interaction
and his experience spans over two
decades
aaron is currently global vice president
and chief design officer at ibm
where he has the ux and design practice
for ibm cloud data and ai
welcome erin it's great to have you here
is there anything else you'd like to add
to your bio
thank you for the opportunity first of
all in just a bite i'll just kind of
summarize on my
own words a little bit about sort of
where i am i lead the user experience
and design org
initiatives and missions for the ibm
cloud data and ai portfolios
i also sort of serve as the chief design
officer for these offerings
and with the intent to create
experiences that hopefully makes a
positive difference to the life of users
i've been lucky enough to graduated from
the field of human computer interaction
and work in ux and design throughout my
entire career
but my experience has primarily been in
the technology space
and i kind of like it because it's a
complex domain
but the problems are not simple ones to
solve
and as designers i think we exist to
help solve
complex problems and it's the constant
changes and challenges that keep things
interesting
for me let's start with the role of ux
in enterprise apps
wikipedia defines an enterprise app as
computer software
used to satisfy the needs of an
organization not individuals
but at the end of the day the software
is used by humans
ux has not been that important in the
past for enterprise apps but that has
changed
can you tell us why and how well i'll
start off by saying that
design as we call it
is really an expression of intent and
intent to solve a problem towards
meaningful outcomes
and so when we say consumer experience
and enterprise experience
at the end of the day we are designing
for human beings and they have a goal
to accomplish by using your software or
your product
so enterprise software in general is
built around the construct of getting
your jobs done
people use it to sort of make a living
so there are additional considerations
that come into play
for example the context and environment
of use
the characteristics and the role of the
user
their specific mental model their
emotional reactions to
you know the general environment that
they work in as well as the
touch points they may have not just with
the product you're building
but also with the other products around
your product
so enterprise software design really
requires a holistic outlook from end to
end
including things like you know
translation and globalization
as well as accessibility so the problem
statement is a little bit wider
and and deeper for enterprise software
but
inherently though i want to still say
that we design for human beings
and it's on us to move consumer
experiences
and then the mental model people have
into the enterprise world
and that's happening more or less in the
last five to ten years as we see the new
workforce coming in
they play with different applications
and they have mobile devices
their attention span is is not at the
highest so
how do we design a enterprise software
experience that they
would use eight hours a day
seven days a week in some cases and just
really
still leave them with a feeling of sort
of
accomplishment so the goal here is be to
transform learn from consumer
experiences and bring in those patterns
of use
into enterprise software let me ask you
about the
major goal still is it having the wow
factor or having standardized
predictable user interfaces that's still
key
well i would say that from the research
we have done
over the years the single most
valuable metric for an enterprise
software
is about productivity how can we
make our users more productive and yes
that includes predictable
elements it includes optimized task
flows to get a job done
it's not necessarily the concept of wow
factor
as a standalone thing at the same time
we as human beings
have emotional reactions to the
environment we are in
the products that we work with so the
goal here would be to
imbibe those innovation
mechanics that we see in the consumer
world into
these predictable learnable interfaces
in the enterprise what is the difference
between ui design
and user experience those words are used
interchangeably but
are they can they be there's probably a
school of debate on this i would say
that
an interface isn't experience
it could be part of an experience but it
isn't experience in itself
so for us to think about user experience
we got to think about
sort of end to end users interaction
with the product the company the
services
and the how the different touch points
come together
to provide a meaningful sort of business
outcome to the users
uh user interface is essentially putting
together
workflows and content
which are very important that's there to
help
users get through from point a to point
b but i feel
ui is a small part of the ux they're
much more beyond that
can you talk now about the evolution
of the user designer the ux designer
role for enterprise apps
going back to my earlier comment about
redesign for humans
but we design for the context of use
enterprise applications have many
different characteristics
for example you're probably designing a
product
that caters to very different sort of
roles or personas
in in my world here for example we've
been designing ibm
cloud and just a simple thing like
let's say billing which as
as a consumer of any software as an end
user you would you'd know
how it works but when you create a
multi-persona
product you need to make sure that the
content you show
and the interaction model you build in
is very specific to the user of the
persona
in my books if you design for everyone
you design for no one
so as an enterprise software designer
you really have to think about not just
the primary paths
but also some of the i want to say the
failover paths as well
you need to also think about instead of
making generalized
experiences do you cater towards a
specific user or a specific persona if
so
do you know what their goals are and can
you use
your software experience to help the
user accomplish the goal
so it requires a little bit of a
different mindset because it's not just
designing the the experience
in a generic sense each persona has a
very different take of
the world and how do we how do you cater
towards those differences that's what
makes it a little harder
so you talked about making sure that
you're meeting the goals of
the different people that will be using
it make sure they're productive
and take the context into account and
you started to talk about
billing as a feature can you tell us a
little bit more
how would you see that designed
differently within an enterprise app and
a consumer app
good question let me just give you the
ibm cloud example
again so ibm cloud for example
has tons of pads and ias services
right it caters to a wide set of
personas
so you've got folks like account owners
and for them it's important to know how
much of the services are being used are
they going to be overcharged
and so on and so forth you also have to
think about
the console of chargeback you also have
to think about
the console of chargeback so if you have
multiple sub teams using your account
uh how much are they using can you
distribute the charges how do i allocate
the usage what sort of currencies and do
we need to support
are there multiple billing systems
involved that we aggregate and bring
together information
so all those complexities is inherently
part of
enterprise software another example i'll
give you is you know the simple act of
signing up right as a consumer i'm sure
you'd have gone in and
gone into website and signed up that's
great you sign up but when you start
using the product would you connect your
ldap
would you need specific accounts and
authorizations in place
would you want to have you know private
or regional
catalogs or services the only specific
users need access to specific things
do you want to account for spend limits
between the different users and their
targeted personas
so that's the other facets of complexity
and i'll give you another last example
is instrumentation is big
nowadays but as you do your
instrumentation of services you also
kind of figured out
the usage model of your users so you
might have built these
great products with the hope that it's
gonna really
bring in a lot of user adoption but
through instrumentation you find out
that that's not really the case
so how can we through meaningful
experience changes
bring the user back to this core
products
so in enterprise software you'll have to
think about all those permutations and
combinations unfortunately
life is not going to be linear that's a
very interesting example
can you tell us how to then retain a
balance
between this goal of productivity and
the business goals
are the challenges there is there a
mismatch in those goals
there are challenges but i want to say
that
if we end up designing
for goals that we expect the user to
perform
everything else will follow and that's a
as a philosophical statement so to speak
but the business metrics of what drives
the product
and the user goals and what they think
is important
even though they may be slightly
different but if one complements the
other i think it's a win-win for both
parts
but the trick here really is to
figure out whether we know the
trade-offs and one way we're doing that
if it's in ibm and in ibm cloud and the
other portfolios was talking about
is through meaningful user research
we really focus our understanding of
user expectations behavior
needs and sort of their motivations to
investigative approaches as well as sort
of qualitative insights
and so once you have that you know what
the goals are and then we
look at the business model and we say
okay
can we map the user goals to business
metrics
and if we can do that i think we're
gonna get a home run so that's been the
sort of the
the take at how we can merge user
expectations and business needs
so let's take the example that you
talked about the billing and the sign up
and talk about designing for multiple
channels or devices
the business goal of course is to let
the customer sign up and look at his
billing
but if you look at it from the user's
standpoint they would like to do it with
their phone maybe with their ipad and
maybe sometimes on the desktop as well
so how do you balance that good question
um first of all
we think that the evolution of usage of
different devices and channels have
changed quite a bit
phones are important smartphones tablets
but
inherently the world is mobile i want to
say
even at your desk you're using a laptop
which you then take
with you to a meeting so it's sort of
everything is becoming portable
now how do we design experiences that
can cross
multiple channels and devices so
a couple of studies we have tried in ibm
in in working through
examples of ibm cloud i can give you a
few examples there but
is to design for responsive experiences
so that the experience can scale across
devices that's fairly common in essence
but in the enterprise world is
fairly complicated you have to support n
number of browsers
you have to support different versions
and releases of browsers
you need to adopt a grid system and and
scale and optimize based on the
grid columns and so on and so forth but
we try to create this experience where
we define the experience
and we scale across devices and in some
cases
we will also build native experiences
in let's say mobile devices that would
inherently
use the the powerful capabilities that
the device provides
you know like the gps functionality the
gyroscope and so on and so forth
but by and large though we want to make
sure that our experience is scale and we
do that by
using a design system that bakes in
a grid system and has a way to scale up
and down
so you did talk about ensuring that the
ux
is geared towards making the user
productive
and at the same time we hear of the need
for making the ux
simple if the ux is simple i also hear
comments like a well designed
application should not require
documentation
so how hard is it to make ux simple is
that the goal
and what about documentation well
making ux simple uh sounds very simple
but it's probably the
most challenging element of it and i
think that's why
we have enterprise designers because
they love solving those problems and
making things
simple making things simple can be
characterized
in different ways we could simplify
experiences by
let's say automating parts and pieces of
it
we can simplify experiences by
implementing
good ai algorithms right that gives
suggestions and recommendations to the
user
while they're doing the job it's not
just about simplifying what you see in
this screen
yes we can do that too right but enter
by software
as i said people use it for a living
eight hours a day for example
and they've been using it for a while so
as we introduce
changes with simplification we kind of
have to find a way to coexist with
mental models that existed from the last
30 years to the
latest in thing and if i if i go back to
your
point about well you know simplicity
does bring in a lot of benefits but at
one cost
i think it's important to remember that
simplicity
is somewhat relative and subjective
to the user who is using it we've had
cases where
for example we've taken a screen
and spread it into multiple step-by-step
screens so we thought all right you know
what
if we guide the user through a process
it might be
more simple and yeah and generally that
that
statement is probably true in most cases
but if you are a heads-down
user who is trying to be productive and
filling a bunch of forms
you know have going through multiple
steps to get your work done actually
slows you down
so that inherent simplicity actually
force you to be
less productive so we gotta again go
back to the the user in the context of
use
and how much of data operations did they
do how much of collaboration did they
need
to then design for experiences talking
about documentation
in technical products yes ideally we
want our users to be able to
walk up a news now i won't be idealistic
to say you can just walk up and use
every product on the planet
but at the very least can we onboard
you the user into our product experience
so that you can
learn a little bit about what's in the
experience and we can progressively
disclose
the different functions as you start
using the product more and more
that we can do and that we should do
however
there is also the domain piece of it as
a user is trying to
work on a particular task they have
different levels of expertise you know
we
maybe they were just just graduated from
school
or they shifted their functional
competency from
you know a network engineer to a system
admin i'm just making an example here
and as you do that their inherent domain
sort of ramp up
you need to have and the lack of that
actually poses a challenge to you as a
user to accomplish your task
so a documentation as we know it in the
traditional sense it's not just about
the features and functions and how we
use it
but i think what we are getting towards
and in ibm cloud we are trying to do
that
is to bring in contextual
user assistance so that the when the
user is trying to do
a job or a task there are different ways
the user can interact with the system
to get help and i'm not talking about
traditional help
i'm talking about contextual assistance
around
knowledge articles that are relevant to
the topic that the user is working in
some recommendations driven from ai on
things that he or she could do to make
it better
as well as interactions with subject
matter experts
all in a single pane of glass so in my
view
documentation as we know it the way we
write documentation
the style the voice and tone is going to
change
the how we consume documentation in our
products are going to change
and also the volume of documentation and
the
i guess the rapid iteration of the
documentation is also going to change
it's hard to make user experience simple
but it's the small things that make a
difference
i'll give just two examples we have this
product called cloud object storage it's
a wonderful product
and with any compute you need you need
to have some storage
right and so again i'm going back to ibm
cloud example here
when we designed it we designed for an
experience that you can go into the
cloud object storage service
and get your job done you can identify
and define a few buckets and you can go
on with that
but we have other services like we have
a cloud and
data platform in that there is a a
tooling
product called ibm watson studio
there you can build and manage your ai
models
now as you subscribe to the service you
need storage as well
and what we found out is that while the
services in itself were great
but they were disconnected the way to
make it simple
is what if you brought in the concept of
subscribing to a storage service and
creating the storage buckets
while you're working on a different
service that linkage and integration
did wonders so now we have co-existing
services that talk to each other it's a
very well integrated set of offerings
the other example is when we have
emerging technologies
like the world of containers and
kubernetes and
in the growing pains of having to learn
them how do you design for
these brand new technology based
experiences
so we we designed the two services in
that brand
the cloud kubernetes service as well as
red hat openshift on ibm cloud very
very focused on modern day kubernetes
based container technologies and there's
a learning curve to it but we managed to
design for it by progressively
walking the user through the technology
so they could
meaningfully use the service and the
result is that in the last
you know 12 months to 16 months we've
had
more than three in international design
awards just on those two products
so yeah there is a trick to it there is
a diligence
and that you need to kind of follow
through but simplicity is
really really hard thanks for that and i
think this section we kind of just
started talking about
the role of ux how it has evolved what
are the things to keep in mind
and to me the two things that stand out
from all that you said
for these questions was that think from
the user's standpoint make sure they're
productive
but for a sign up flow for example you
probably don't want to do it in multiple
steps even though it sounds
like the right thing to do but for
something that you're adding in
complexity
and making it more progressively more
difficult maybe that's a good idea so
there are patterns but you should be
careful in when and where you use them
is that a fair summary yeah i mean
bottom line you should know your user
if you do then you'll be able to design
the experiences
towards that let's talk a little bit
more now about
process how do you structure the ux
process you know how do you create road
maps if it's a new product or an
existing product let's start with that
so within ibm we are lucky enough
and fortunate enough to have a mindset
of a client base or user-centered design
and development and to do that
we created a enterprise design thinking
framework
which by the way is available for anyone
to use
and that has sort of three
i want to say high level characteristics
the first is the principles that guide
us
and so we decided that our focus will be
on user outcomes
and we're going to be inventing and
reinventing and iterating all the time
and we'll do that with meaningful
diverse teams and that's an intentional
decision as
when we form teams to create projects
they are diverse by definition diverse
in expertise
reverse in talent diverse in
perspectives and
all the elements of diversity then we
talk about the loop and
loop is a is a testament to our
constant iterative design and build
mindset
that we observe our users in their
natural habitat on how they do
their job etc to really understand their
environment in their their
pain points etc we reflect on that
and then we make we create designs and
experience
and we do that over and over again
and on the on the more structural
approach
we have a concept of the keys and these
are things that
help with with defining the making of
getting alignment and things like that
for example we have a concept of hills
hills are are like mission statements so
as a team
we got to know who we are designing our
products and experiences for what goals
are they trying to accomplish
and what's so great about it what is the
differentiation factor so that's all
combined into the concept of hills
we have a console of playbacks where we
have this
diverse team that work with internal
external
users to come in and provide a point of
view so
we have a lot of these sort of playbacks
in in motion
um at different stages of the product
definition phase and design phase build
phase and even
post build phase as well and the in the
last and probably the most important
thing
is the console of sponsor users these
are our
not stars these are people that we
design for
so instead of trying to design on the
side we design and develop
with our users so it's a co-creation
perspective so all of this is baked into
the ibm
enterprise design thinking framework and
that's what helps us
sort of move forward so you talked about
designing with
users how is that different or is it
related to user research
um well it's it's it's it's sort of
complementary and it's it's additive i
mean
i want to say so user research is really
about
getting to know users expectations and
behaviors and such and then
validating your designs along the way
really getting a take of the mental
model
measuring the success of your designs
and whether users can complete the task
successfully whether they can do it
within a
realistic time frame that's all user
research so that is this formative
and summative and subjective set of
studies that we do
sponsor users are people who are
involved with
us throughout the journey they're
involved with the requirements
that go along in defining the product
and as we define the product to a
sponsor users we then take the designs
and do more user research with
prospective sort of users
or target personas so that we get more
sample data and we bring the data back
in we share it back with responsive
users
so that we know that once we're done
building this
product or service it will be successful
sponsor users also have a i want to say
a skin in the game
because they are affecting and
influencing the direction
of the product so it's complementary
user research is about the techniques
that we use to kind of get the right
kind of data
and sponsor users are the people we work
with to help define
our products so in terms of user is a
little bit more so
what else is part of that is the sales
team involved with user research
what is the role of data how do you
collect the data
so user research is a wide gamut of
um i want to say
techniques and tools from all the way
from contextual studies where we
go in and look at the users and how they
are
using their system in their environment
to more sort of facilitated
brainstorming
and to get at their wants and needs to
the other end of the spectrum
of benchmark studies how long did they
take to complete their tasks et cetera
in addition to that we look at
instrumentation data
so how are users using our products
where are they getting
stuck where are the blockers to
conversions
to more subjective things like
desirability studies if you build this
thing for you
mr misuser would it be meaningful for
you would you desire to get it
so there are different facets of data we
bring in
through this user research sort of
cellular tooling now
we do collect data before during
and after the production of our products
and experience because as
as i said with enterprise design
thinking we believe in the loop
nothing is ever done we constantly
iterate so even
in the sales cycle we we go and work
with our sales teams to figure out
as they talk about our products and
services
and they manifest um these experiences
and demos and other such
vehicles of of sharing what is the kind
of feedback they're getting
what are the perceptions of the product
because sometimes perceptions becomes
reality and so we have to account for
that in building our experiences
we talk to our marketing teams we find
out what sort of campaigns they're
running
and what what is the messaging of the
product there's a messaging of the
product
jive with the value proposition of what
the end user is trying to do
if not there's a mismatch when you need
to bring it together
we work with the customer support team
we take a look at the let's say the
support tickets that people have been
filing
over the years on similar products and
try to learn from it
so we have touch points at pretty much
every phase of the journey
whether it across different competencies
whether it's marketing whether it's
engineering whether it's product
management whether it's customer
support sales and even documentation so
it's sort of a team sport
at this point
become an autonomous digital enterprise
and your business can achieve a game
status
intelligent predictive systems
effortless automation
and technology and people working in
harmony
this is the autonomous digital
enterprise
visit bmc.com a-game for more
information
so how do ux teams then quantify their
contribution to the business
if it's a team sport good question
there's always this
never-ending question on the roi for
user experience
with the advent of digital experiences i
think it's become a little bit more
concrete we can
do different measurement studies of the
current state
and the future state and show the
difference for example
if you look at the conversion rate of
how many people are coming into
let's say ibm cloud as an example
and registering for it and becoming an
active trial user today versus if you
did this design excel design
why what will it be and based on that
it's pretty easy to show the impact the
other things around
customer satisfaction as we go through
the different journeys
with our users we constantly tune and
optimize our product experiences
and throughout that process we collect
different kind of customer feedback
in product like net promoter score and
we can see
how the sort of chronology of the net
promoter scores have been improving over
time
right we can also say that the support
cases are going down
between releases and part of it is
attributed to great experiences
we can also see that the number of trial
user
conversions is going up which means
sound for onboarding flows that we
implemented
is also working well so there are now
specific
metrics we can glom on in the business
world to show
design impact so you decided on the
metrics
then do you do comparison between the
design a and the design b
all the time all the time
again we don't believe in any perfect
design there isn't anything like that
in my view but we believe in constant
iterations of designs and and
the the advantage of having these
diverse themes i was talking about
is that we do get very different point
of view on how we can solve a problem
and so we do this a b testing all the
time
sometimes in production so when we went
with
ibm cloud we designed a new dashboard
right
and the dashboard was meant to give a
personalized experience for the
different users that come into our
public cloud
it could be a developer it could be a
data scientist or it could be an account
admin
and based on the need they want to see
different things so when we were
designing the dashboard we had probably
three different designs
and we tested them with different sort
of samples
in production to figure out which is the
best route and then we chose the one
that was
gaining the most momentum and went with
it that was just one example
we do that even and during the design
phase
where we design multiple variations of
designs
and then get different kinds of user
feedback to
pretty interesting experimental design
to make sure that
the sanctity of data is there and then
come back with realistic data
so we're getting more data driven as
well right it's not just about
experimentation
which we do all the time but also make
sure that we can get the data
interpret the data and then use the data
to make our products better
the one question to me though is that
this sounds like a lot of
work so how do you then utilize that
for multiple projects do you have
convert those into components and
patterns guidelines
yes to all of those questions
we have a huge portfolio in ibm software
even in public cloud i mean public cloud
we got
tons of pads and iis services we got
data and ai services we got apps so we
got the gamut
and the challenge here is how can we
be consistent with not just our look and
feel but also the way
it works at the same time how can we get
our developers more productive our
designers more productive
to spend time solving the complex
challenges and problems versus you know
going into details of every little
widget that exists in the screen
so to help with that we have a design
system
the ibm design system that bakes in a
design language
and that has a component library that we
call the carbon design system
that's got all the web components and
we're building in some
mobile ones as well as well as design
patterns so patterns are reusable
sort of use cases package to assembly of
different sort of components
we also have guidelines baked in as well
as visual assets
and we use this carbon design system to
help make sure that our products are not
only consistent
but we have a same way of of solving the
problem across different domains
the design system if you want to check
it out is carbondesignsystem.com
it's also open source so many external
folks are contributing to it so
we believe in sharing back attack this
is one way of doing it
so you guys should take a look at it
but design system is one big factor of
it
how we have scaled up we've also
introduced a lot of sort of
learning vehicles to make sure our our
engineering corner parts are very
aware of the different you know
conceptual design system
how to implement a grid system
appropriately
we've also given a lot of guidelines
around usage so it's one thing giving
components and
patterns but then you can also use the
parallels in the wrong use case so
we've come up with a list of sort of
obvious use cases to map into
and we have a cross-functional across
the corporate ibm wide
team whose job is to always call for
new patents that we need or changes to
patterns
because our life is evolving so we're
going to see a more growing set and as
we build more patterns
more teams are going to use it and we're
going to become more and more consistent
ibm cloud went to this journey a huge
journey
of going through design systems so with
the current
adoption of the carbon design system you
know you will start seeing
almost all of our services have some
common fabric
not just a look and feel but the
specific use cases and patterns are
going to be
similar and whether you're in a path
service or an is service or in a
database or you're looking at some ai
models
you inherently get the feel that they're
part of the same ecosystem
you have similar patterns that bind them
together
we'll put a link in the show notes to
the design palette
so if i could summarize uh this section
about process what i get is that
the focus is on an outcome and the
outcome is defined
with the help of a set of metrics some
of them could be
things like the number of srs which
sounds like it's
better for the company though it also
certainly helps the user in that they
have
less srs to log and track and the bad
experience in just having to log in sr
but at the same time then you work with
diverse teams
along with sponsored users in a loop so
that you're constantly testing the
design patterns
once you know what works and you convert
that into components and patterns and
share that across teams
is there something you want to add to
that is that the fair summary
yeah it's a fair summary i just want to
add that on the business side
you know we look at net retention rate
and things like that so
if we have a user who's using a service
for a while
and they're not going to renew why not
can we
do something in the experiences that
entice them to stay
so i think we are getting into the
business of design as i call it
from just an executional pace to design
being
an element to the strategy of the
company
so that we can bring in more users we
can spread user adoption
but also keep users actively using our
products and services
so over the last you know 10 years or so
the ux and design competency maturity
has
has grown up quite a bit right it's no
longer just wireframes
and icons is really about experiences
and now it's about the business element
of those experiences
so the metrics there are pretty
important yep
let's uh talk now about the organization
structure
so how does the ux evolve in different
companies of different size is it
different in a startup company versus a
mid-sized company versus a large company
you know there is never a single
organizational structure that
will work across the board there is so
many variables
that define the success of your design
org structure serum
in ibm where i am we have a
pretty robust mechanism in place where
product management
engineering and design are sort of
equal peers and we work together on not
just the strategy but also the execution
and to enable to do that i i do have a
centralized organization here
but the designers are embedded in
mission so
day in and day out they're working
towards the vision of the product for
the service
and that's a great working model for a
large company like ibm we have
distributed
we have design studios globally
we have different products in different
domains so
if you were completely siloed it won't
work because
you know we would end up you know
building very sort of
myopic experiences so the challenge we
had was how do we scale up the
profession how do we
sort of see the forest for the trees and
how can we scale
by working with each other even though
we are in different parts of the world
so centralized model but in execution
embedded with the teams is the way to go
right now now i've seen i've worked in
different places
i've seen in centralized model
decentralized model there are pros and
cons in all of them
so i would say that depending on the
culture of your
company the awareness of what design is
and what design does
the talent and craft the buy-in the
level of investment
these are just some variables that
decide on how you're going to function
but all that is not as important as
making sure that if designers are put in
an
environment wherein the stakeholders and
the partners
actually believe in good design is good
business
then the ark structure is kind of
irrelevant
so to speak so that's what we need to
get into now when you think about
product life cycle you may have
a bunch of mature products in in your
company
and for that you the problem statement
is kind of set
so the kind of design that you do and
the kind of studies that you run
is going to be fundamentally different
from if you're building a net new sort
of a
blue sky organic product for that you
need to do some more upfront research
you need to kind of
really work on defining the requirements
from the ground up
so the structure you might have there it
could be different
so again my point here would be that
i've seen decentralized centralized both
work
it depends on the context and the
variables i talk about
but at the end of the day i feel like
the design profession is nimble enough
to be able to work under each of those
variations and permutations
so you didn't mention that the role of
the designer or the design itself
changes if it's an initial product
definition
it's an enhancement that said i'd like
to talk about the role of ux engineer
with the dev team running scrum
in that case would you say that the ux
engineer should be part of the team or
is that still centralized
so when we start talking about teams
there is a
whole element of competency craft
and career involved right
in the execution of a project so
i'm just to give an example in ibm cloud
we have the designers sitting in the
sprints
individuals principal services every day
they're in the scrum calls
right they're the scrum of scrums they
are part of the backlog grooming
part so agile and enterprises and
thinking
we kind of merge them together so that
we can
kind of help with the overall mindset
because we tend to believe that
design thinking is isn't just for
designers it's a way to solve problems
and get alignment
so we spread the goodness across the
board and we've also changed our
execution model
to make sure that regardless of where
organization you might report into etc
you're part of the the same sprint
team and um the design is being in a
different perspective the ux engine is
bringing a different perspective on how
things should work
and but it's handled and at that level
and
when we up level it to at the product
level
we start looking into things like design
and user experience
quality reviews that we have started a
lot which is to make sure that
the things that we ship out of the door
are something that we could be
proud of are we making sure that
when we ship something out of the door
they're going to be usable
by our end users to do that we do a lot
of these sort of
internal reviews we involve stakeholders
from
not just design but also the different
competencies marketing sales support etc
to come in and see it in action so that
they could all influence the product
direction
and that's happening in addition to any
of the org models we have in place
so i almost want to de-emphasize the org
structure
perspective to how things can work
regardless of that
that's it the team has a product owner
and the ux designer so who actually
makes a final decision
typically is it the product owner or the
user designer
so if it's about features and functions
it's the product owner
if it's about how the feature and
function needs to be manifested
in terms of an experience we do have the
design lead
weighing in if it's about what kind of
technology
should be used and constructed to make
the function id
happen in the product that's on the
engineering team right
so each one wears a different hat and
that's the power of this three-in-a-box
thing that i'm talking about
is each competency bring in a different
perspective at the end of the day
the product manager is the product owner
he or she will make the final
business calls but we want to make sure
that the different competencies that
come in
in the making of have an equal say so
that we don't trade off
one facet over the other let's talk now
a little bit about the differences when
you're designing
for micro contents that may be built by
different teams and
these micro contents come together to
the whole ui
versus cases where you have a dedicated
team building just the ui
and other teams building the back ends
i think it's it's very rare to have
dedicated team who just work on the
front end and they don't interface with
the back end i think to have an
experience
you need to have the backend
architecture ready
to be able to consume the events and the
triggers and the data models that are
built in it
to manifest itself in the product so
you know just a is a quick sort of
example we we
are working on this cool project called
ibm satellite you know
it's a kind of a distributed cloud it
extends ibm public cloud in
private data centers and other public
clouds and we got
sponsor users from telco and banking all
coming in to kind of
help with the definition off in the
making off and in that
experience setting as we're working
through our backlogs and a roadmap and
you know what goes in first second third
the design
team the product management team and the
technical team
are sort of locked in step if you attend
that meeting you won't be able to tell
who's representing which
competency so that's the power of great
alignment and i think with great
alignment we will get better outcomes
so but at the end of the day there are
some business decisions that need to be
made and sometimes designers
have a tendency to keep designing for
over and over again
because they're not quite happy where
things are but there is the trade-off of
time
and go to market so that's where the
product manager comes in and give it
gives a perspective right
so it is a i want to say a
team effort at the same time the product
manager acts as a business owner
to make the right trade-offs let's end
the section with
a question about stakeholders what can
stakeholders do to support
and help make this function more
successful
first of all stakeholders probably will
need to
better understand what is design and
what can design do i think there's a
whole myth about design is just about
wireframes or it's a pixel on a screen
or it's an icon or
making something look pretty it's so
much more
so the level one is there a good
understanding of
what design is and what design can do
part two in this day and age we have to
assume
that user experience is one of the big
differentiators or can be
because if you compare competitors they
kind of have similar features
you know the price points are kind of
similar the economic state is kind of
similar as well so what else can be the
differentiation
it's the user experience the third is
stakeholders need to understand that
nowadays
user experience is also the
i want to say the uh the main barrier
for
user adoption so if you want our
products to be
widely successful we need to make sure
our experiences are great so
are we ready as a stakeholder partner to
design
to trade off features
and experiences in other words promote
experiences
and build more features along the way
right are we ready to try
different ways of solving the problem do
we want to give the creative freedom
to the design team to come up with ideas
that you evaluate
with data to be able to change the
direction of the product so can
can you think about the role of a
designer beyond
what they just do for a living which is
to produce user experience designs
so a lot to go in there but more or less
it's about understanding the role of
design
and what design can do switching gears
now to
conversational ui and ux why has there
been a need for this ui paradigm
and what are the pros and cons from
yourself need
well i want to say there's always been
conversational
interfaces but it wasn't mainstream
so for example if you have a script
running on your command line
is it a conversational interface i would
argue it is kind of
if you build in arguments and comments
in it
but as users are nowadays used to
kind of more social interactions all
over the place
they want to feel like they're
interacting with the system so we
you know go from a system of record to a
system of engagement
for a system of engagement there needs
to be some
back and forth sharing and communication
between the user and the system
so that has come to the forefront now
and
also in addition to that as we bled in
the the field of ai and how ai can
really help with
making our our systems and users more
smarter etc
there is even a wider need to understand
not only what the ai does but how you
can interact with it and
some of it the human way of doing it is
to do through conversations
so there's always been a need we've had
labs in the past but now it's kind of
mainstream
and the people are used to using sort of
social conversations to
get work done in this social world and
their point is how do we make
the same thing happen in the enterprise
pros and cons
in the world of productivity as i was
mentioning earlier
where users are trying to complete a
particular task
not all of these tasks are going to be
adaptive
to a conversational interaction model
right there are specific use cases
specific considerations
in place on how you build and design
good conversation experiences
not everything is cut out to be
conversational
maybe some form filling probably it is
but when you in a deep engagement
reality or building an app
for example using our ibm cloud services
you can use conversational ux to
supplement collaborate with people's
systems decided to
help make your underlying sort of
artifact better
but the act of completing the task is
probably not going to be conversational
but at the same time if i look in the
the other end of the spectrum
to make sure that the newer generation
workforce that's coming into the
companies and starting to use their
tools to ensure that they have the same
level of engagement with their
enterprise software systems
versus you know their their personal
access to consumer
devices and apps and such is to build in
the engagement in the enterprise
software through conversational
experiences
through voice and tone through micro
interactions
through proper content design so there
are different elements of it not just
conversational experiences
so i feel there's a little bit more to
be done because
i'm not 100 sure that there is
a lot of trust with conversational
systems when end users work with
conversation systems sometimes the
the output back from the conversational
experiences are
are not accurate so that that erodes
stress
sometimes the voice and tone is very
generic so
that doesn't help either so we feel like
there's a lot more to be done in the
conversational experiences field
but i can almost guarantee that this is
going to be mainstream for the next you
know
10 years or so until until there will be
a no ui no conversational experiences
what is the importance of the design and
the copy for
conversational ui what what you actually
design
the copy is well you design for the
interactions you design for the
responses you design
for the way you verbally communicate you
design
for the keywords that the user might
interact with
you design for the tone that the users
might be conversing you
in right so copy becomes
hugely important when i say copy i mean
the voice and tone
as well as the structure of the content
the sequence and how it's delivered
the brevity of it all of these things
matter
and i would also say that conversational
design
is a new enough field and new in the
sense that i think
we as designers need to learn more
understand better principles so it's a
growth area for designers too
if you just take a traditional designer
who does great
job in designing let's say enterprise
software or consumer software
and you say hey the interaction model
has completely changed it's going to be
conversational experience
go design it i think they'll have a hard
time they will have to ramp up they'll
have to understand the principles the
behavioral elements
that make up the constructs of a good
conversational experience
so technology aside i think the
technology is coming in
design we need to learn a little bit
more more patterns
need to be established i want to say of
conversation experiences
and then the the trick would be to
figure out how can we
tie in the conversational experiences to
the jobs to be done for the user
so if we connect those two dots there
will be more adoption of conversation
experiences
so definitely not today and you
mentioned 10 years
but eventually do you think that this
paradigm will make screens obviously
i don't think we'll have screens
absolute ever
can we cut down on the number of screens
and
the interaction sort of models might
differ might change
but there is this element of you know
seeing is believing sometimes
and so some of the user interfaces will
still be there even though they may be
the secondary ways of interacting
as humans develop more trust in using ai
and they would want to converse with ai
and they're getting meaningful
trustable unbiased responses then
they'll start
using it more and more but i think
that's the feel that as i said you know
five to ten years
that's where the field needs to harden a
little bit but i don't see
you know physical user interfaces or
digital user interfaces just
disappearing thanks erin so let's move
on to our last topic for today which is
career path what does a new engineer
need to do to work towards a career as
ux design
let's take a specific example
design has multiple i want to say
sub competencies so
there is this world of user experience
and interaction design
how things work there's this world of
service design there's this world of
content design there's this world of
visual design
there's this world of information
architecture
there is this world of user research
or usability engineers so it's
a pretty wide selection of
competencies you might want to get to so
depending on where you're coming from
there's your background you might be
more
i guess more at ease in picking up
one of these versus being a generalist
to be a journalist you know it takes
time and effort but it
reaps some dividends as well but i would
say that the first thing is to
learn a little bit more about what is
designed there's enough material out
there
i i love the niels and norman group they
have a lot of
great learning materials on design and
experience and give it a shot there
go take a look at some of the design
systems uh i would recommend carbon
design system for example
and then aside from the whole
education part of it you can learn a lot
on the job
so if you're breaking into the field of
design see if there are other designers
around you
if there are work with them shadow them
ask
them to come in and and just share
the work that they're doing and you find
some time and effort to critique the
designs and get some feedback
so there are ways to kind of learn and
adopt but at the end of the day if you
love solving problems and you want to
use
experience as a way to mitigate the
problem and you
inherently have empathy for the users
that we're targeting
then this is a great field to be i have
designers with
behavioral psychology background i have
designers who have
background from the banking industry i
have designers who
have been trained clinical psychologists
i have
designers who are from the service
design world
i have designers who used to be software
programmers
as they're coding away systems and
solutions
they decided that their passion lies in
not just the technology but how you
manifest the technology and experiences
so there is no specific
sort of blocker for you if you want to
break into design you just have to pick
the path that
interests you more if you want to know
more about users
how they work really get into the head
that is the user research field and it's
a great field
and if you're more interested in okay
i'm going to break down
the the learnings from research into
tangible experiences then maybe ux
design
is is the way to go about or you may say
i've got
great sort of i and a talent for
a visual language ability to provide
a brand an identity and a singular point
of view to a product then maybe
visual design is the way to go so you
have many different avenues
but the good news is you can start from
where you are so what do i expect as a
career path as a ux designer
it would be the same as a mainstream
career like an engineer you start off
with a
entry level you scale up to be
a team lead in a design lead in ibm we
have these
unique sort of paths as well which is
pretty
industry leading we have this concept of
design principles these are
technical well-known design
practitioners
and we have a few of them in ibm beyond
design principles you can be a
distinguished designer
these are designers who are known for
their craft and
have a very specific skill and can scale
across ibm
so you can be an individual contributor
you can be technical
design owners as design principals and
distinguished designers
up to a design fellow right so we got a
great career curve
now is that standard in the industry i
would say
most of it is except i'm not so sure
about the design principle piece of it
but there is a very defined career curve
for most mature companies that have a
design competency
in ibm we definitely do i used to work
at oracle
a while back there definitely was a
career curve
i'm willing to bet most big companies
actually have a career curve
let's wrap up now i think that was a lot
of good feedback to there and things
about that
um how can people contact you the best
way would be to link in
i think that's that's a good start but
more than contacting me i i also have a
set of medium publications that i
tend to write from time to time on
different perspectives on design and
designing for enterprise or new
technologies so that's another way to
interact with me but um shoot me a note
over linkedin and i'll i'll
be happy to respond we'll put your
linkedin in the show notes
is there anything you'd like to talk
about that we did not cover today
uh not really i think you covered good
grounds by
parting message to the audience is thank
you for listening
just remember that design is an
expression of intent
and if we have the right intent we can
provide experiences together
that makes enterprise software equally
relevant
and equally engaging and at the end of
the day
design profession has the i want to say
the charter
and the responsibility to design ethical
experiences so let's work together
towards a
world wherein there is no bias in
anything that we do
thank you thanks for that perspective
thanks everyone for listening
become an autonomous digital enterprise
and your business can achieve a game
status
intelligent predictive systems
effortless automation
and technology and people working in
harmony
this is the autonomous digital
enterprise
visit bmc.com a game for more
information
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at
se-radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on linkedin
facebook twitter or through our slack
channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening